Hello, my friends.
And welcome to exercise number 10.
And this exercise, we are asked to find the time complexity of this method.
This print by taking an array in array as a parameter and having a nested loops to be executing a system
that does print by.
So post the video and think about this exercise.
And please write down the solution of this exercise and try to solve it.
And the list your solution in the comments below.
So let's start solving this exercise.
Exercise, please pay attention, as I told you in all the previous exercises, when you see a for loop.
Please watch out the initial condition, the stopping condition and the increment of function and the
increment continues.
We start by this loop, this loop would be executed.
Let me put it right or drawing again, this.
Would be executed from I equal to zero.
Okay.
And I time and less than a red dot length.
And I plus plus think about a red dot length would be an OK.
We refer a red dot length as an end or as M.
In all the exercise, we start from zero to N and O and I + +, therefore this slope is executing its
code from zero to N, and it is not jumping over the elements it's executing all the elements of and
therefore the outer loop would be of complexity of and it's very simple.
Now the inner loop here.
For.
We start from Jay Equal to I +1 one.
So here we are, going to introduce another trick and your trick inside this inside the complexity.
OK, so there is a new pattern here introduced so into the are equal to I +1.
And the J less than N and J Plus Plus.
So the inner law in any alo would be from I +1 tell and.
OK.
This pattern for loop is very common.
It's it's important that, you know, the on time and that you deeply understand that you cannot rely
on just memorizing common quarantines times.
Deep comprehension is important.
OK, so
continuing the iteration the first time through J runs for KN minus one step and the second time it's
and minus two and then and minus three steps.
And so therefore the number of steps is thought for the first iteration.
When you need to solve like these examples, you cannot solve them by understanding and memorizing the
common things and the common runtimes.
OK.
You need to make, and they're all on paper this and try to see that iteration.
Table four are equal to zero.
This I.
This is J.
When I equal to zero j starts from zero plus one.
So the first time J is one I will put equal to eight.
OK and is equal to eight.
J is one.
And this is the result.
Jay is equal to one.
Yes.
One less than eight.
OK, go and rent buy.
OK.
The second iteration, NJ, would start from two and so on, printing hereby and hereby, and so on.
OK, from one do tell reaching seven because eight is less.
Seven less than eight, but eight is not less than eight.
And the stopping here for the first iteration of is I again going up increasing.
I buy one.
It's now one.
Now Jay here is equal to one plus one starts from two.
This time it starts from two.
So I equal to one.
Jay equal to two.
And and it is constant buy here.
It will result two, three or four till seven.
And.
And so on.
So if we do do J, we'll go from three and to seven.
So I will put here the result.
If we go from.
I start from I equal to zero.
J will start from one and stops at seven.
It will, if we go from what are equal to one, J will go from two to seven I from three to seven.
If we took three, J will go from four to seven here from four, five to seven.
Five, it will go from six to seven.
And.
Six, it will go from seven to seven, seven it will be executing one time.
And if we go from seven.
Jay will not execute.
OK.
OK, so here we have how many times this year this have been executing a number of times.
We print by, OK, we execute the system that out the brain.
Here we have seven times.
OK, here we have.
Five, sorry, six, five, five yes or no?
There's here five.
Sorry.
Seven is included.
Yes, one, two, three, four, five, six and seven, three, four, five, six and seven.
This executed four times three, two and one.
OK.
Like, these exercises are very important because you need to get that pattern.
You need to see it to understand the part.
The sum of of four one through and minus one.
This is n minus one because n is equal to seven and j executed to n minus one.
This is and minus one.
Seven.
MJ represent and minus one and seven in.
I represent
like an.
OK.
No.
And.
How many times these are executed?
Think about it.
Alternatively, we can figure out there on time by thinking about what the code means.
Iterate through each burst of values I and J where J is bigger than I there are and the square total
purse.
OK.
In in an ordinary, the nested loops.
Where I equal to zero and less than and equal to zero and less than we are executing and a square which
is for in this case.
And the square, which is.
If we took an equal to eight, so we have eight, eight digits here and eight digits here.
OK, we have 64, 64 times, but now in our case, we are not executing the whole thing.
We are executing the part of this.
So let's let's clarify again, if we have like and the square when paired equal to n equal to a we have
here.
These are the purse.
We have eight columns.
And aid throws.
OK.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven and eight.
Sorry.
So we will start from here.
If we have any square, we are going to go through all of these digits.
OK.
But since.
We have this type of algorithm.
We start from equal to zero.
Think about I as here as iterating through here and we start from I equal to zero.
And Jay, equal to one who is so we will occupy this.
OK.
We will start from this, I read through it with better for a better understanding.
So let's start with I hear.
I for the Rose and J for their columns if I.
And, Jay, are we are starting from zero and tell, and so we should add like color, all of these
cells, but since we are following a different pattern, we start from eye equal to zero.
This is equal to zero.
And.
This are equal to zero and equal to one, so this cell is not is not filled, so we are going to fill
this for equal to zero.
We are going to execute seven times the system without the prison cell.
So all of this from water from one till seven are being executed.
So this is what was zero one two three, four, five, six and seven.
All of these will be colored.
And these are executed carefully.
All of this, but the first cell is not executed.
If we move into a equal to one.
Three, four, five, six and seven.
If we move into equal to one, J is executed from two to seven.
So the first two cells are being empty and we are going to execute from cell equal to one and Cell J
equal to do so.
From here we start.
We execute all of these.
OK.
And these are being executed.
It's very simple.
Now we move and to do.
Are equal to two J is executed starting from three.
It's very simple and we move through all of this.
Jay Equal are equal to three.
We move from four and we start executing from four.
OK.
It's very simple.
OK, guys, you need to master this algorithm by understanding how you are driving and from where you
start and when and the way you increment this.
When I equal to five or four, J is starting from five, it's very simple.
When I equal to five J is increase the executive from six and they'll seven, when I is equal to six,
J is executed only one time because J is equal to seven when I equal to seven J is not executed any
time.
So this is a very different from executing a nested loop where the complexity of it and before there
for the outer loop and the inner loop is n since here we are following a different path.
If all of N Square is executed in this condition, we are going to colour all of these cells.
In the table, but here we are doing a very different pattern.
These are only a that we have colored are being executed, so we are following a pattern here.
We are following a pattern where I equal to zero j is equal to one.
So always j is incremented by one is increased by one.
And in all the cases and over, I OK, this looks like half of this matrix is being executed, which
has size roughly and squared over two.
OK.
So whole.
If we color all of this matrix, we could result in the square.
But this metrics is half of it is is executed, so we need to multiply by half.
OK, so half of this matrix is being executed.
Therefore, it takes all of the square time.
So the average what we know that the outer loop runs and times, how much work does the inner loop does
do?
It varies across the iteration, but we can think about the average iteration.
What is the value?
The average of the value of one two three four five six seven eight and nine 10, the average value
would be in the middle.
So it is roughly five.
OK.
We took an example about eight, and it is roughly four.
What about one two three two one?
So the average value of this sequence is and over two.
So therefore, according to this metrics, according to this drawing, according to the iteration,
we are executing half of this matrix.
So that the complexity of that inner loop is.
Is an over two.
So that complexity of the inner loop is over and over to OK because we are executing half of that code.
OK?
We are executing half of the code that we should use.
OK.
Because I equal to zero every time it is increased and J is increased by one.
So this would result in the matrix here.
Then like this matrix?
It's 64 cells.
If we get an equal to eight, then we have we had 64 cells and we are executing half of these cells,
which which is 20, is 32 at times printing the system to tie out the print by.
So we are printing 32 times the pie here.
OK.
If we execute this.
But since we have an above, we need to multiply and times and and over two times all of one.
Therefore, we have that.
The final complexity is is n times n minus one over two.
And all of and squish.
OK.
It's very simple.
And one important thing that I should remember to you that and minus one because we are summing the
integers of one through and and on run time.
OK.
So we are getting from one to n minus one because here we are not being.